To conclude this module I want to say a few words about how RSA is used in practice.
为了完结本章，我想说几句关于应用RSA的
So first of all, if you want to speed up RSA encryption,
首先如果大家想加速RSA加密
it's perfectly fine to use a small encryption exponent e.
那么使用较小的公钥e是没有问题的
So rather than using a random e one can use a small value of e
可以不使用随机的e，而是选择一个小e
and in fact the minimum value that's possible is e=3.
事实上最小的可能值是e=3
So it's not difficult to see that the smallest possible value for e
不难看出e的最小可能值
is in fact e=3. And let's see why.
事实上e=3.我们来看为什么
Well e=1 is a bad idea because that's not particularly hard to invert with e=1.
e=3是一个不好的想法，因为e=1的逆不难去求
e=2 is not a valid RSA exponent because remember in the definition of RSA,
e=2不是一个有效的RSA指数，因为记得在RSA的定义中
e had to be relatively prime to phi(N). phi(N), if you remember, is (p-1) times (q-1),
e必须与Φ（N）互质。如果大家还记得，Φ（N）=（p-1）(q-1)
which is an even number. If p and q are odd primes,
是一个偶数。如果p和q都是奇数
(p-1) times (q-1) is an even number, but if e is even, if e is equal to two,
那么（p-1）(q-1)是一个偶数，但如果e是偶数，如果e=2
it's not going to be relatively prime to phi(N). So e=2 is not valid either.
e就不与Φ（N）互质，那么e=2也不是有效的
And then e=3 is the first minimum value that can be used,
那么e=3是第一个最小的可以使用的值
and then we just have to make sure that in fact, p is
equal to two mod three,
然后我们必须确保事实上，p=2 mod 3
and q is equal to 2 mod 3 so that (p-1) times (q-1) is not divisible by 3.
q=2mod 3，这样（p-1）(q-1)就不会被3整除
So in fact this is a fine public exponent to use,
那么事实上这是一个可使用的很好的公钥指数
however the recommended value is 2 to the 16  plus 1. So 65537.
不过推荐的值是2^16+1，即65537
It's a good idea to use this recommended value of e.
使用这个推荐的e值是个好点子
To compute x^3 mod N, you would basically need three multiplications.
计算x^3 mod N，你需要三步乘法
To compute x^65537 mod N using repeated squaring, you would need 17 multiplications.
而计算x^65537 mod N，使用重复平方算法，需要17步乘法
Basically what you would do is you would repeatedly square 16 times
你重复平方16次
and then you would multiply by x one more time.
然后再乘一次x
Ok? So just with 17 multiplications you can do this exponentiation,
那么只要17次乘法，你就可以计算出这个指数
so this is still much, much faster than using a random e,
那么这比使用一个随机e要好得多了
which would require something like 2000 multiplications.
随机e需要约2000次乘法
So this leads us into what's called the asymmetry of RSA,
那么这就让我们得到了RSA的非对称性
where in fact encryption is quite fast: encryption only requires 17 multiplications.
事实上加密是很快的：加密只需要17次乘法
However decryption is much, much, much slower;
但是解密要慢的多
it requires something on the order of 2,000 multiplications.
它需要约2000次乘法
I should point out that there is a standard trick for slightly speeding up RSA decryption.
我应该指出，有一个标准的加速RSA解密的技巧
This is called RSA-CRT; this stands for RSA with Chinese remaindering.
叫做RSA-CRT；叫做带中国剩余的RSA
It's a method for speeding up RSA decryption by about a factor of four,
这个方法可以让RSA解密加速4倍
but nevertheless it's still gonna be much, much, much slower than encryption.
但不管如何这依然比加密慢很多
The ratio of encryption to decryption on RSA is roughly a factor of ten to thirty,
RSA的加密与解密的速度比，差不多从10到30
so encryption could be up to like thirty times faster than decryption, depending on the size of your modulus.
那么加密速度可以是解密的30倍，但取决于模的大小
Interestingly, this is a special property of RSA where encryption is so much faster than decryption.
有趣的是，这是一个RSA的特殊性质，加密比解密快很多
And other public key systems--for example, in the
next module we're gonna look at ElGamal encryption--
另一公钥系统，比如说，我们下一章要看到的EIGamal加密
don't have this property where both encryption and decryption take roughly the same amount of time.
就没有这个性质，它的加密和解密用时差不多一样
We've already discussed key lengths for RSA before.
我们之前已经讨论了RSA的秘钥长度
So I just wanted to flash these numbers to remind you that if you're using a 128-bit AES key,
那么我只想展示一下这些数，以提醒大家，如果你使用128位AES秘钥
really, you should be using a 3,000-bit modulus.
你应该使用一个3000位的模
Although everybody just uses a 2,048 bit modulus.
尽管大家都用2048位模
And if you're really using a long AES key, like a 256 bit AES key, the RSA modulus gets to be quite big.
如果你真的使用一个长AES秘钥，比如256位，那么RSA模将会很大
Now, I wanted to mention a number of implementation attacks on RSA.
现在我想提醒一下众多的针对RSA实现的攻击
These are attacks that have been demonstrated against particular,
这些攻击已将针对特定的
mathematically correct implementations of RSA. However, these implementations were vulnerable
RSA的数学上正确的实现成功展示了。但是这些实现
to certain side channel attacks that make the implementation completely insecure.
对特定的旁道攻击是脆弱的，这使得这个实现是完全不安全的
So the first example of this is due to Paul Kocher back in '97.
打一个例子是Paul Kocher 于1997年提出的
He showed a timing attack where all you do is you measure the time for an RSA decryption.
他展示了一个计时攻击，你只需要测量RSA解密的时间
And simply by measuring the time, you can actually expose the secret exponent d.
通过简单的测量时间，你可以揭露密钥指数d
And so, this says that if you are going to implement an RSA decryption,
那么，这是说你实现了RSA解密
you had better make sure that the decryption time is independent of the arguments.
你最好确保解密时间和这些参数无关
Another attack also by Paul Kocher two years later showed that
Pual Kocher两年后又提出了另一个攻击展示了
if you have a smart card that's implementing RSA decryption
如果你有一个智能卡，上面实现了RSA解密
you can actually measure the power consumption of the card while it's doing RSA decryption
你能测量这张卡在做RSA解密时的功耗
and then simply by looking at the peaks and troughs you can literally read off the bits of d
通过观察功耗峰谷，你可以读出d的各位
one bit at a time as the smart card is running through the repeated squaring algorithm.
一次读一位，当智能卡在运行重复平方算法时
So using a power analysis attack it's actually fairly easy to get the secret bits
那么使用一个功耗分析的攻击，是容易获取密钥各位的
of the secret key unless the smart card defends against power analysis attacks.
除非智能卡能提抗这些功耗攻击
And finally another attack called a fault attack shows that the RSA is very vulnerable to
最后，另一种叫做错误攻击的展示了RSA对解密错误是脆弱的
decryption errors and in particular, if for some reason an error occurs during an RSA decryption,
特别的，如果出于一些原因，RSA解密时发生了错误
one error is actually completely enough to reveal the secret key.
一个错误将完全泄露密钥
So this attack is actually fairly significant. It's just, one error completely reveals your secret key.
所以如果这个攻击真的是很重要的，也就是说，一个错误将完全泄露你的密钥
And as a result, many cryptolibraries will actually check the result of the RSA decryption
因此，许多密码学库都会检查RSA解密的结果
before returning it to the caller. And the way you would check it is,
在返回结果调用者之前。检查的方法是
you would take the output of this exponentiation, and simply raise it to the power of e,
取出这个指数的输出，计算它的e次方
and check that you actually get back c modulo N.
检查是否又回到c mol N
And if so, you know that your decryption was done correctly.
如果是这样，说明这个解密是正确的
Now the reason you can do this is because again, e is much smaller than d,
现在可以这么做的原因是，e比d小很多
therefore checking takes much less time than actually raising something to the power of d.
因此检测此比计算d次方要花的时间少得多
Nevertheless, you know, even though checking is ten times faster than the actual decryption,
不过，即使检查比实际解密快十倍
this still introduces a 10% slowdown. And so sometimes this is actually turned off.
这依然引入了一个10%的开销，所以有时这一功能实际上被关闭了
But nevertheless, it's actually a good idea to check that your RSA output is correctly computed.
不过，检查RSA输出的计算是否正确，的确是个好方法
And so all these attacks kind of again make the point that if you just implement RSA naively
那么所以这些攻击再次说明了，如果你自己实现了一个RSA
it would be mathematically correct, it would work,
它在数学上是正确的，它能工作
however there would be all these potential attacks on the implementation
但是针对实现，依然会有这些潜在的攻击
and as a result you should never implement RSA yourself.
因此，你不应该自己去实现RSA
Always, always use standard libraries and just use the implementation available there.
始终使用标准密码库，始终使用已有的实现
So to be concrete, I wanted to show you an example of one of these attacks.
具体地说，我想给大家展示一个这些攻击的例子
And in particular I'll show you the fault attacks on RSA.
特别的，我会给大家展示RSA上的错误攻击
And again, this will be a fault attack on what's called RSA with Chinese remaindering.
这也是个错误攻击，是针对带中国剩余的RSA
So in fact, as I said at the beginning of the segment, RSA decryption is often implemented as follows:
事实上，如我在本节开头所说，RSA解密经常是如下实现的
What you do is, you decrypt the cipher text c modulo p, then you decrypt the cipher text c modulo q.
解密密文c mol p，然后解密密文 c mol q
And then you combine the two to actually get the decryption modulo N.
然后结合两者得到模N的解密
And this combination is done using what's called a Chinese remainder theorem.
这个组合是通过中国剩余定理做到的
Which I'm not going to explain here but it's not too difficult to see how that works.
我这里不解释细节，不难看出这是如何工作的
Basically, once you have the result of the decryption mod p and the decryption mod q
一旦你有了模p和模q的解密的结果
you can combine it to get the decryption mod N.
把它组合起来获得模N下的解密
And it turns out this gives about a factor of four speed up
实际上这给出了一个4倍的加速
over the naive implementation of directly doing the exponential modulo N.
比起直接使用模N指数的实现来说
Okay. So, let's see why this is vulnerable to faults.
好了，那么我们看为什么这对错误是脆弱的
Suppose it so happens that when your decryption library is computing the decryption modulo q,
假设当你的解密算法库在计算模q解密时
for some reason the processor makes an error.
出于某些原因，处理器犯了一个错误
And, actually, what it gets is not the correct xq. It gets an incorrect xq,
实际上这不是一个正确的xq，得到的是错误的xq
so let's call this xq hat. However when it computed the decryption modulo p,
那么我们叫这个为xq^，不过当它计算模q的解密时
you know, no error occurred. So these errors are fairly infrequent.
没有错误发生，那么这些错误很少
And so let's just assume that an error occurred modulo one prime
我们只假设，计算一个质数模时，发生了一个错误
but it did not occur modulo the other prime.
但没有发生其他首相模。
Well, if that's the case our computation is correct modulo p and incorrect modulo q.
如果是这种情况：我们的计算是正确的模p和不正确的模q。
That says when we combine the two results we're actually going to get an output,
这就是说当我们把两个结果合并到一起将得到一个输出，
I'll call it x prime, such that the output is correct modulo p.
我会叫它基x，这样输出就是正确的模p。
So, x prime is really equal c to the d mod p but is incorrect modulo q.
所以x是相当于c对d模p而不是模q。
If we raised both these equations to the power of e, what we obtain is the following two relations.
如果我们把这两个方程加到e上,我们获得的是以下两个关系。
Well, let's see. This guy we raise it to power of e.
好，让我们来看看。我们把它加到e上。
What happens is the left hand side becomes x prime to the e.
发生的是左手边将是x对e.
The right hand side, here, it's c to the d.
右手边，它是c对d。
If I raise c to the d to the power of e--e and d, remember are inverses of one another--
如果我把c加到d到e-e,d,记得是相互的逆――
And as a result, if I raise c to the d to the power of e, both exponents cancel out and I simply get c back.
因此，如果我把c加到d到e，都是指数抵消，我会简单地得到C。
So I know that x prime to the e is equal to c. But modulo q, there was a mistake.
所以我知道x模e相当于模c.但模q，这里会出错。
So x prime to the e is not equal to c modulo q.
所以x模e不等于c模q.
So therefore, if I look at this difference, x prime to the e minus c.
因此，如果我看到了这个不同，
We know that it's zero modulo p, and it's not zero modulo q.
我们知道它是0模p，不是0模q
So now if we compute the GCD of this value with N, what do we get?
所以现在如果我们计算出这个值和N的GCD，我们会得到什么呢？
Well, as I said, this is zero mod p, but it's not equal to zero mod q.
正如我说的，这是0模p，但不等于0模q。
Which means that this quantity here is divisible by p, but is not divisible by q.
也就是说这个值可被p整除，但不能被q整除。
So therefore when I compute the GCD, what I'll get is simply p.
因此当我计算GCD时，我将会得到的是p。
And again, this is because p divides this quantity here when q does not divide this quantity.
这是因为P可以将这个值划分开，而q不能。
So now basically what I have just obtained is the factorization of N.
所以我获得的是N的因子分解。
Once I have the factorization of N I can compute phi(N)
一旦我有了我能算得的N的因子分解phi（N）
and then given phi(N) I can actually compute myself the decryption exponent from the public key.
然后鉴于φ(N)我可以自己计算出公钥的解密指数。
So now I have just recovered the secret key from the public key
所以现在我只要从公钥中恢复出私钥
from a single mistake that happened during decryption. So this is why typically
从一个在解密中发生的简单错误中。
when you do RSA decryption it's a good idea to check the results
这就是为什么当你做RSA解密时它是一个很好的想法来检查结果
especially when you use Chinese remaindering to speed up RSA decryption.
当你用中国剩余定理来加速RSA解密。
The last attack I want to talk about is a very recent observation
我想讨论的最后一个攻击是一个很近期的观察，
that was observed by Heninger et al and Lenstra et al
被Heninger et al 和 Lenstra et al观察到的
that shows that RSA key generation can be problematic when it's done with bad entropy.
来展示RSA密钥生成模式会出问题当它被一个错的信息熵做的时候。
So here's how things go wrong. So the way open SSL generates RSA keys is as follows.
这里就是事情怎么出错的。Open SSL生成RSA密钥如下。
Well, it starts by basically seeding the pseudo random number generator.
它是由伪随机数生成器的种子开始的。
And then it uses random bits from a pseudo random number generator to generate the first prime p.
然后它使用随机比特从伪随机数生成器生成第一个数p。
Then it will go ahead and seed the random number generator some more,
那么它将继续，生成更多的种子随机数生成器,
and will generate bits from the pseudo random number generator to generate q.
并且将产生一些由伪随机数生成器生成的字符来生成q。
And finally, it will output the product of p and q.
最终，它会输出p和q的生成值。
Okay so the two steps, where we see the seed the pseudo random number generator.
所以这两步，我们看到种子伪随机数生成器。
Now suppose that this is implemented on a router or a firewall of some sort,
现在假设这是被应用在某种形式的路由器或防火墙,
and suppose that the key generation happens right after the firewall starts up.
假设密钥生成模式发生在防火墙开启之后。
So the firewall boots up. At the time of the boot, there's not a lot of entropy
防火墙启动。在启动的时候，在伪随机数生成器中不会有很多熵。
in the pseudo random number generator, and as a result
在伪随机数生成器中不会有很多熵。
the firewall is likely to generate a prime p that comes from a very low entropy pool.
因此防火墙很可能生成一个数p，来自一个低熵池。
Which means that this p is gonna be one of a small number of possibilities.
也就是说这个p将是可能出现的一小组数中的一个。
However, after we've generated p, generating the prime actually takes a little bit of time,
然而，在我们生成p之后，生成基数会花一点点时间，一些微秒。
a few microseconds. And so, by then the firewall will have generated more entropy
到时候防火墙会生成更多的熵
and so after we add more entropy to the entropy pool,
所以当我们把更多的熵加到熵池之后，
the prime q say is generated from a much larger entropy pool and is therefore unique to this firewall.
基数q会从一个更大的熵池中生成，而且对于这个防火墙是唯一的。
Now the problem is that many different firewalls if they generate an RSA key
现在的问题许多不同的防火墙都用这种方式生成RSA密钥
in this way many of them will actually end up using the same prime p but a different prime q.
导致它们使用了相同的素数p和不同的素数q
So what this says is that if we look at two RSA moduli from two different firewalls, N1 and N2.
如果我们来看两个不同防火墙的RSA模，N1和N2
If we compute the GCD of N1 and N2, well both of them had different q's but the same p.
如果我们计算N1和N2的GCD，当两个都有不同的q和相同的p时
So if we compute the GCD, actually we will end up with a factorization of N,
如果我们计算GCD，我们就得到了N1和N2的因式分解
of both N1 and N2 and then we can actually figure out the private key both for N1 and for N2.
然后我们就能找到N1和N2的私钥
So this has actually been observed in practice.
这已经在实践中被观察到了
Both of these groups, what they did is they scanned the web
这两个团队通过扫描网络
and recovered all of the public keys out there that are used on various web servers.
恢复了各种网络服务器使用的所有公钥
They then ran a massive GCD, using some arithmetic tricks
然后他们计算大量的GCD，并使用了一些算法技巧
they were able to compute this massive GCD of all pairs of public keys N1 and N2.
使得他们能计算大量的公钥N1和N2对的GCD
And lo and behold, they actually realized that a fair number of these keys have a common factor.
他们意识到有相当数量的密钥有相同的因子
So they were actually able to factor these moduli.
所以他们能够分解这些模
So in the experiment, they were actually able to factor about .4% of all public SSL keys.
在这个试验中，他们实际可以分解0.4%的ssl公钥
This is an amazing fact, that, in fact, so many web server public keys out there
这是一个惊人的事实
are vulnerable just because they happened to generate the RSA key using low entropy.
如此多网络服务器由于碰巧使用低熵生成密钥而存在漏洞
So they have a common factor with somebody
else's factor
因此它们与其它服务器有相同的因子
and GCDing the two together gives you the factorization.
求这两个的GCD就得到了因式分解
So, the lesson from all this is when you generate keys,
这给我们的教训是，当你生成密钥时
no matter whether they are RSA keys or ElGamal keys or symmetric keys,
无论是RSA密钥，或ElGamal密钥，还是对称密钥
it's crucial that the number--, that your generator is properly seeded.
很重要的一点是生成器要适当给予种子
So don't generate keys immediately after start up. You have to kind of make sure
所以不要启动后马上生成密钥
the seeding of the generator has had enough time to actually generate enough entropy.
你需要保证给予生成器种子有足够时间生成足够熵
And only then you can start generating keys. So this is a really nice example
然后才开始生成密钥
of how a, a bad random number generator can mess up your RSA public keys.
所以这是一个很好的例子，说明随机数产生器如何搞乱你的RSA公钥的
Okay so this is the end of our discussion of public encryption from RSA.
好的，RSA公钥加密的讨论就结束了
I wanted to mention a few further readings if you want to read more about this.
如果你想知道更多，我想提及几个拓展读物
So there's a nice paper by Victor Shoup that talks about why
有一篇Victor Shoup的很好的论文讨论了
chosen cipher text security is so important in the public key settings.
为什么选择密文安全在公钥设置中如此重要
So if the Bleichenbacher attack wasn't convincing enough, there are many other attacks like this
如果Bleichenbacher攻击说服力不足
that are possible if you don't use a chosen cipher-text secure system.
如果不使用选择密文安全系统，这里还有一些其他类似可能攻击
So if you want to learn more about chosen cipher-text security,
那么如果你想知道更多关于选择密文安全的知识
please look at Victor Shoup's paper.
请看Victor Shoup的论文
There's a survey that I guess I wrote a couple years ago, that looks at many different attacks
这是我在几年前写的一个调查，研究了RSA系统的许多不同攻击
on the RSA system. I guess I wrote this when RSA was twenty,
我写的时候RSA有20年历史
I actually need to update this to 30 years of attack on the RSA cryptosystem.
我需要更新到30年内的RSA系统攻击
There've been some developments in the last decade, but for now this is actually a decent survey
近十年来有了一些发展，但这仍然是个很好的调查
to look at and read about more attacks on RSA.
可以了解更多的RSA攻击
The OAEP results that I mentioned are referenced here, OAEP reconsidered.
我在这里提到了OAEP，OAEP的再思考
And finally, if you're interested in key length analysis of RSA and other public key systems,
最后如果你对RSA和其他公钥系统的密钥长度分析感兴趣
there's a nice paper by Arjen Lenstra that discusses how you should choose
这份很好的Arjen Lenstra的论文讨论了如何为公钥系统选择密钥长度
key lengths for your public key systems, and even for your symmetric key systems.
甚至为对称密码选择密钥长度
Okay, so those are the four references. I hope you have time to look through them.
好的，这就是4个参考资料。希望你有时间看看这些
And I will stop here. And, in the next module we're going to look at
到这就结束了。下一节我们将会来看
another family of public key encryption systems, this time based on discrete log.
另一种基于离散对数公钥加密系统